{"QandAList":
	[
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is Normalization?","answer":"In relational database design, the process of organizing data to minimize redundancy is called normalization. Normalization usually involves dividing a database into two or more tables and defining relationships between the tables."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is De-Normalization and when would you go for it?","answer":"As the name indicates, de-normalization is the reverse process of normalization. It is the controlled introduction of redundancy in to the database design. It helps improve the query performance as the number of joins could be reduced."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What's the difference between a primary key and a unique key?","answer":"Both primary key and unique enforce uniqueness of the column on which they are defined. But by default primary key creates a clustered index on the column, where are unique creates a non-clustered index by default. Another major difference is that, primary key does not allow NULLs, but unique key allows one NULL only."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is candidate key, alternate key, composite key?","answer":"A candidate key is one that can identify each row of a table uniquely. Generally a candidate key becomes the primary key of the table. If the table has more than one candidate key, one of them will become the primary key, and the rest are called alternate keys.A key formed by combining at least two or more columns is called composite key."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is a transaction and what are ACID properties?","answer":"A transaction is a logical unit of work in which, all the steps must be performed or none. ACID stands for Atomicity, Consistency, Isolation, Durability. These are the properties of a transaction."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"Explain different isolation levels","answer":"An isolation level determines the degree of isolation of data between concurrent transactions. The default SQL Server isolation level is Read Committed. Other isolation levels (in the ascending order of isolation): Read Uncommitted, Read Committed, Repeatable Read, Serializable."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is Lock Escalation?","answer":"Lock escalation is the process of converting a lot of low level locks (like row locks, page locks) into higher level locks (like table locks). Every lock is a memory structure too many locks would mean, more memory being occupied by locks. To prevent this from happening, SQL Server escalates the many fine-grain locks to fewer coarse-grain locks."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What's the difference between DELETE TABLE and TRUNCATE TABLE commands?","answer":"DELETE TABLE is a logged operation, so the deletion of each row gets logged in the transaction log, which makes it slow. TRUNCATE TABLE also deletes all the rows in a table, but it will not log the deletion of each row, instead it logs the de-allocation of the data pages of the table, which makes it faster. Of course, TRUNCATE TABLE can be rolled back."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What are constraints? Explain different types of constraints.","answer":"Constraints enable the RDBMS enforce the integrity of the database automatically, without needing you to create triggers, rule or defaults. Types of constraints: NOT NULL, CHECK, UNIQUE, PRIMARY KEY, FOREIGN KEY"},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is an index? What are the types of indexes?","answer":"Indexes in are similar to the indexes in books. They help the query optimizer retrieve the data quicker.Indexes are of two types. Clustered indexes and non-clustered indexes. When you create a clustered index on a table, all the rows in the table are stored in the order of the clustered index key. So, there can be only one clustered index per table. Non-clustered indexes have their own storage separate from the table data storage. Non-clustered indexes are stored as B-tree structures (so do clustered indexes), with the leaf level nodes having the index key and it's row locater. The row located could be the RID or the Clustered index key, depending up on the absence or presence of clustered index on the table."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What are the pros/cons of using Indexes?","answer":"If you create an index on each column of a table, it improves the query performance, as the query optimizer can choose from all the existing indexes to come up with an efficient execution plan. At the same time, data modification operations (such as INSERT, UPDATE, DELETE) will become slow, as every time data changes in the table, all the indexes need to be updated. Another disadvantage is that, indexes need disk space, the more indexes you have, more disk space is used."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What are the steps to improve performance of a poor performing query?","answer":"There could be a lot of reasons behind the poor performance of a query. But some general issues are: No indexes, table scans, missing or out of date statistics, blocking, excess recompilations of stored procedures, procedures and triggers without SET NOCOUNT ON, poorly written query with unnecessarily complicated joins, too much normalization, excess usage of cursors and temporary tables. Some of the tools/ways that help you troubleshooting performance problems are: SET SHOWPLAN_ALL ON,SET SHOWPLAN_TEXT ON,SET STATISTICS IO ON, using profiler/query analyzer."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is a deadlock and what is a live lock? How will you go about resolving deadlocks?","answer":"Deadlock is a situation when two processes, each having a lock on one piece of data, attempt to acquire a lock on the other's piece. Each process  would wait indefinitely for the other to release the lock, unless one of the user processes is terminated. SQL Server detects deadlocks and terminates one user's process. A livelock is one, where a  request for an exclusive lock is repeatedly denied because a series of overlapping shared locks keeps interfering. SQL Server detects the situation after four denials and refuses further shared locks. A livelock also occurs when read transactions monopolize a table or page, forcing a write transaction to wait indefinitely."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What are statistics, under what circumstances they go out of date, how do you update them?","answer":"Statistics determine the selectivity of the indexes. If an indexed column has unique values then the selectivity of that index is more, as opposed to an index with non-unique values. Query optimizer uses these indexes in determining whether to choose an index or not while executing a query.Situations under which you should update statistics: If there is significant change in the key values in the index or if a large amount of data in an indexed column has been added, changed, or removed (that is, if the distribution of key values has changed), or the table has been truncated using the TRUNCATE TABLE statement and then repopulated."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What are the different ways of moving data/databases between servers and databases in SQL Server?","answer":"BACKUP/RESTORE, Detaching and attaching databases,Replication,DTS,BCP,logshipping,INSERT...SELECT,SELECT...INTO,creating INSERT scripts to generate data."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is database replication? What are the different types of replication?","answer":"Replication is the process of copying/moving data between databases on the same or different servers. SQL Server supports the following types of replication scenarios:Snapshot replication, Transactional replication (with immediate updating subscribers, with queued updating subscribers),Merge replication"},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What are cursors? Explain different types of cursors. What are the disadvantages of cursors? How can you avoid cursors?","answer":"Cursors allow row-by-row processing of the resultsets.Types of cursors: Static,Dynamic,Forward-only,Keyset-driven.Disadvantages of cursors: Each time you fetch a row from the cursor, it results in a network roundtrip, where as a normal SELECT query makes only one round trip, however large the resultset is. Cursors are also costly because they require more resources and temporary storage (results in more IO operations). Further, there are restrictions on the SELECT statements that can be used with some types of cursors."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is a join and explain different types of joins?","answer":"Joins are used in queries to explain how different tables are related. Joins also let you select data from a table depending upon data from another table.Types of joins: INNER JOINs, OUTER JOINs, CROSS JOINs. OUTER JOINs are further classified as  LEFT OUTER JOINS, RIGHT OUTER JOINS and FULL OUTER JOINS."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What are triggers? How many triggers you can have on a table? How to invoke a trigger on demand?","answer":"Triggers are special kind of stored procedures that get executed automatically when an INSERT, UPDATE or DELETE operation takes place on a table.Triggers cannot be invoked on demand."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is Stored Procedure?","answer":"A stored procedure is a named group of SQL statements that have been previously created and stored in the server database. Stored procedures accept input parameters so that a single procedure can be used over the network by several clients using different input data."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What are the advantages of using Stored Procedures?","answer":"Stored procedure can reduced network traffic and latency.SP execution plans can be reused, staying cached.They help promote code reuse,encapsulate logic, and provide better security to your data."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is View?","answer":"A simple view can be thought of as a subset of a table. It can be used for retrieving data, as well as updating or deleting rows. Rows updated or deleted in the view are updated or deleted in the table the view was created with. It should also be noted that as data in the original table changes, so does data in the view, as views are the way to look at part of the original table."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is the difference between a Local and a Global temporary table?","answer":"A local temporary table exists only for the duration of a connection or, if defined inside a compound statement, for the duration of the compound statement.A global temporary table remains in the database permanently, but the rows exist only within a given connection. When connection is closed, the data in the global temporary table disappears. However, the table definition remains with the database for access when database is opened next time."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is BCP? When does it used?","answer":"BulkCopy is a tool used to copy huge amount of data from tables and views. BCP does not copy the structures same as source to destination. BULK INSERT command helps to import a data file into a database table or view in a user-specified format."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What command do we use to rename a db, a table and a column?","answer":"To rename DB: sp_renamedb 'oldname' , 'newname'. To rename Table: sp_rename 'oldTableName' 'newTableName'.To rename Column: sp_rename 'TableName.[OldcolumnName]', 'NewColumnName', 'COLUMN'"},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is an execution plan? When would you use it? How would you view the execution plan?","answer":"An execution plan is basically a road map that graphically or textually shows the data retrieval methods chosen by the database's query optimizer for a stored procedure or ad-hoc query and is a very useful tool for a developer to understand the performance characteristics of a query or stored procedure since the plan is the one that database will place in its cache and use to execute the stored procedure or query. From within Query Analyzer is an option called 'Show Execution Plan'. If this option is turned on it will display query execution plan in separate window when query is ran again."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is RAISEERROR?","answer":"RaiseError generates an error message and initiates error processing for the session."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is PIVOT and UNPIVOT?","answer":"A Pivot Table can automatically sort, count, and total the data stored in one table or spreadsheet and create a second table displaying the summarized data. The PIVOT operator turns the values of a specified column into column names, effectively rotating a table. UNPIVOT table is reverse of PIVOT Table."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What are Aggregate Functions? ","answer":"Aggregate functions perform a calculation on a set of values and return a single value. Aggregate functions ignore NULL values except COUNT function. HAVING clause is used, along with GROUP BY, for filtering query using aggregate values.Following functions are aggregate functions.AVG, MIN, CHECKSUM_AGG, SUM, COUNT, STDEV, COUNT_BIG, STDEVP, GROUPING, VAR, MAX, VARP"},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is Row_Number()?","answer":"ROW_NUMBER() returns a column as an expression that contains the row's number within the result set. This is only a number used in the context of the result set, if the result changes, the ROW_NUMBER() will change."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is the difference between UNION and UNION ALL?","answer":"The difference between Union and Union all is that Union all will not eliminate duplicate rows, instead it just pulls all rows from all tables fitting your query specifics and combines them into a table."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is B-Tree?","answer":"The database server uses a B-tree structure to organize index information. B-Tree generally has following types of index pages or nodes:Root node: A root node contains node pointers to branch nodes which can be only one.Branch nodes: A branch node contains pointers to leaf nodes or other branch nodes which can be two or more.Leaf nodes: A leaf node contains index items and horizontal pointers to other leaf nodes which can be many."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What are Cursor Variables ?","answer":"Also called REF CURSORS.They are not tied to a single SQL. They point to any SQL area dynamically.You can declare variables at Client side and open them Server side. You can thus centralize data retrieval."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"Why use Truncate over Delete while deleting all rows ?","answer":"Truncate is efficient and faster. Triggers are not fired and also deallocates space but doesn't affect the table structure.TRUNCATE resets identity of the table."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is an inline view?","answer":"It's a subquery in the FROM clause with an alias that can be used as a view within the SQL statement."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What are Nested and Correlated subqueries ?","answer":"The subquery used in WHERE clause is a nested subquery. If this subquery refers to any column in the parent statement, it becomes a correlated subquery."},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is an implicit cursor?","answer":"Oracle opens an implicit cursor to process each SQL statement not associated with an explicit cursor.Few implcit cursor attributes: %FOUND, %ROWCOUNT, %NOTFOUND, %ISOPEN, %BULK_ROWCOUNT, %BULK_EXCEPTIONS"},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"What is the use of DBCC commands?","answer":"DBCC stands for database consistency checker. We use these commands to check the consistency of the databases, i.e., maintenance, validation task and status checks.Eg:DBCC CHECKDB,DBCC CHECKALLOC,DBCC CHECKFILEGROUP"},
				{"category":"Sql","topic_id":"19","question":"How to find the Nth highest value from a table?","answer":"select * from Table A where n =(select count(distinct Column) from Table B where A.Column<=B.Column)"}			
	]
}